Guide to the William George Stewart Papers 1827-1931 (bulk 1838-1859) MS 594
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1827-1860
  - Miscellaneous, 1848-1855 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Correspondence relates to Stewart's business arrangements including those with Juan de la Granja. Frequent correspondence with Luis Bossero.
  - Miscellaneous, 1845-1855 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1839-1846 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Frequent correspondence with William Hagar, Eliza J. Stanton, and Daniel Mossier.
  - Miscellaneous, 1847-1855 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Some correspondence addresses the efforts to build a telegraph in Mexico.
  - Miscellaneous, 1845-1859 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Frequent correspondence with Henry Makepeace regarding the telegraph in Mexico.
  - Miscellaneous, 1842-1857 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1838-1857 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Frequent correspondence with Luis Bossero. Material related to printing business and Stewart's work as Vice-Consul for Mexico.
  - Miscellaneous, 1841-1852 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1840-1859 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Includes letter from Juan de la Granja to President Santa Anna of Mexico. Materials addressing Mexican-American War.
  - Miscellaneous, 1842-1856 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1842-1855 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1844-1855 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Some correspondence addresses Juan de la Granja's death. Agreement between Henry F. Makepeace and William George Stewart for the construction of telegraph line in Mexico.
  - Miscellaneous, 1843-1856 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Frequent correspondence with Pedro Giol concerning sale of Tabascos.
  - Miscellaneous, 1843-1845 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1843-1849 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1841-1852 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Frequent correspondence between Juan de la Granja and F. Stodart. Materials addressing printing business.
  - Miscellaneous, 1845-1860 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Frequent correspondents include: Joaquín Múñoz y Múñoz, J. A. Ingram, Daniel Henarie, and Juan de la Granja.
  - Miscellaneous, 1842 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series II. Financial documents, 1836-1859
  This series includes accounts, invoices, and shipping papers related to William George Stewart's businesses and personal finances. There are records of Stewart's transactions as a merchant including trade reports of the goods that left from New York to Mexico. These also contain accounts of the ships leaving the port, the people aboard them, and their captains.
  In addition, there are materials associated with Stewart's business dealings in printing. These comprise records of what publications are sent to Mexico as well as receipts from subscriptions to certain printed matter. There are also agreements between Stewart and publication companies such as the "Courrier des États-Unis." Box 10, folder 5 contains a copy of the patent for the R. Hoe single cylinder printing machine.
  Furthermore, the series includes personal financial material such as records of Stewart's own purchases, debts, and income. There are legal documents and financial agreements that Stewart took part in as well. Box 10, folder 1 also contains documents related to the Mexican Consul in New York Sebastian Mercado.
  Much of the documents are written in Spanish.
  An additional account book with information from 1852-1854 that was used as a commonplace book later in the century can be found in Series III.
  Series II is roughly arranged by chronological order. It is important to note that some of the dates overlap therefore, the order was determined by the earliest dated content in each folder. Most folders have not been altered from the arrangement they were found in by the processing archivist in July 2019. However, items that were not originally found in folders were arranged by similarity of content.
  Additional checks, receipts, and promissory notes are placed at the end of Box 11.
  - Exports from New York to Mexico (4 folders), 1838-1841 (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
  - Exports from New York to Mexico. Oversize, 1841 (Folder Oversize-Large)
  - Consul of Mexico, 1838-1842 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Materials related to Juan de la Granja and Sebastián Mercado, the Mexican Consul in New York.
  - Bills to pay, 1841-1842 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Business statements, 1843-1846 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Trial balances, 1845-1847 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - R. Hoe & Co. Single Cylinder Printing Machine, 1846 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Withdrawals and shipments (2 folders), 1846-1851 (Box 10, Folder 6A-6B)
  - Checks, 1846-1856 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Checks, promissory notes, and receipts, 1846-1856 (Box 11)
    Three bundles located at the end of Box 11.
  - Account book, 1846-1848 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Agreements, 1847 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Invoices, 1847-1849 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Invoice book, 1848-1849 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Protests, 1848-1852 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Stock account, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Ocean Bank account book, 1849-1852 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Debts, 1849-1852 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Purchases and exports, 1849-1859 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Includes records of publication exports to Mexico.
  - Miscellaneous, 1851-1852 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Printing business, 1850-1854 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    Materials related to "Los cuatro postrimerias del hombre."
  - Purchases, 1847-1857 (bulk 1855-1856) (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1836-1859 (bulk 1855-1856) (Box 10, Folder 17)
    Includes receipts, records of purchases, and business correspondence.
- Series III. Later materials, 1852-1854, 1878-1931
  Series III includes materials that relate to later generations of the Stewart family, especially a Mary and a Sarah Stewart. These include an account book from 1852 to 1854 that was later used as a commonplace book during the 1880s. Within this book there are pieces of poetry as well as miscellaneous papers. In addition, there are letters addressed to either Mary or Sarah Stewart. The series also includes items related to a Mrs. Jones and a R. McKean Jones.
  It is important to note that items found within the commonplace book were removed and placed into archival folders. The original location of the items is noted on their enclosure.
  - Miscellaneous later documents, 1909-1931 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes records of purchases of a Mrs. Jones and mail addressed to Mary and Sarah Stewart.
  - Commonplace book (1 of 4), 1878-1909 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Includes transcription of lecture by Henry Ward Beecher from December 22, 1882.
  - Commonplace book (2 of 4), 1878-1909 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Commonplace book (3 of 4), 1878-1909 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Commonplace book (4 of 4), 1878-1909 (Box 11, Folder 7)